Hello, this is Manner Code.
Software is complicated.
First of all, there is a lot of code to write. The
example project created for this series alone
has over 12,000 lines of code. If it is an
actual operating service, even a
small service, it will easily exceed 100,000 lines.
100,000 lines is the amount of code in 20 novels.
Writing a long code is not the end. You have to
keep fixing the code you wrote. This means that if you
fix A, B breaks down, and if you
fix B, A and C break down. To use an analogy, it is like a horse
crying while trapped in a Rasputica.
At this point, you feel the need for design.
However, when you actually try to write a design document, you realize that
expressing the thoughts in your head in detail is
not as easy as you thought. Even a sheet music, a
document that visually records sound or music, is
this complicated. It is not easy to express not only music but also various concepts such as
finance and logistics
and abstract user requirements
in a concrete model.
Fortunately, UML was born in the late 1990s
to overcome the difficulty of modeling abstract concepts.
Grady Bouch led the way.
We use UML with anticipation. Let's
draw a class diagram.  I
also draw sequence diagrams,
but when I
actually try to design them, it does
n't seem to be much different from coding them directly.
Why is that?
This is because the thought process is accustomed to implementation. It is
because it transfers implementation-level thoughts into UML rather than gradually concretizing abstract concepts. Just as
knowing how to read sheet music does
not enable you to compose music,
learning UML does
not give you design skills.
Therefore, in this series, I will show you
how to concretize abstract requirements and
connect code through a real project. I
chose movie ticket reservations as the domain.
Movie ticket reservations are a familiar domain for most people, so they are easy to understand and
include various functions such as login, payment, and seat selection, making them a
suitable example. The
basic topic of this article is software design, but I will
also cover test-driven development.
Modern development environments basically support testing tools. Even if you
look at famous open source projects, they
have a certain level of testing.
This means that testing is important and highly utilized.
However, in reality,
many cases do not even properly implement test automation, let alone TDD. It is by no means easy to
write meaningful tests without any preparation.
This is possible only when you have software design capabilities.
Therefore, I decided that it would be efficient to cover design and TDD together.
Now, let's start the first meeting of the project.
Since this is a small project, there are
two participants. The
one on the left is the domain expert, and the one on the right is the test automation expert.  I'm a developer. The
domain expert tells us a lot about the system we need to build.
We operate about
4,000 theaters nationwide, and that number
could increase in the future.
Currently, we only support movie ticket reservations, but we
plan to add large-scale performance tickets in the future.
And the important thing is that seats cannot be double-booked.
In the past, our customer service center had a really hard time due to that problem. We
also have a lot of accumulated movie information and review data, so
this data must be maintained. The
conversation here is well-organized, but in
reality, more information will be
conveyed in a disorganized manner.
However, we need to listen carefully to the stories that come out at the beginning of the project, because they are the
most important requirements.
The developer listens to the domain expert and asks
a few questions. When do you plan to add the
large-scale performance ticket reservation feature that you mentioned
?  I'd like to know if this should be
included in the scope of this project in advance
or if it's not something I should consider yet.
And does keeping existing data
mean not changing the DB system?  Are
there any other services currently sharing the DB?
As you can see from the DB, the
domain expert is not a developer, so the
technical expressions are vague.
These things need to be carefully checked by the developer. The
domain expert answers the developer's question like this. There is no specific schedule for the
large-scale concert ticket reservation function
yet.
However, I think it would be good if you could consider it a little this time so that we can upgrade without much difficulty when the function is added in the future. The
DB is not used anywhere else but our service. As long as the
data is well maintained, changing the system itself is not a big problem. From what I've heard, it
seems that we don't need to worry about the content regarding large-scale concerts. It is
not the scope of the project, and the
requirements are not clear. I don't know
when it will be needed, but it is an
issue that needs to be reviewed again when it is needed.
Even if it is not documented, you should not forget to tell the
domain expert that you will carefully consider large-scale concerts.
Understood.
Then, the large-scale concert ticket reservation function will
not be one of the top requirements for this project.
Instead, we will pay close attention to making it easy to expand the function later during the development process. Do
n't worry.  It's
important to get along well with someone who believes in you.
Through our conversations so far, we've
summarized the top priorities as follows. We begin the project by interpreting and organizing the
information provided by the domain expert
from a developer's perspective.
Once you've roughly established the project's goals with the domain expert, it's
time to name the project.
First, ask the domain expert for their opinion.
What should we name the project?
It's a movie reservation system.
How about just the Movie Booking System?  I do
n't like it. I'll
worry about large-scale performances. Let's
use the Movie Booking System.  yes?
Okay,
thank you.
Domain experts might want a Korean project name.
However, from a developer's perspective, since
all terms, including the project name, are
directly implemented in the code, it's
easier to define them in English if possible. It's
important for developers to faithfully follow the domain expert's requests, but they
also have the responsibility to coordinate the project in an efficient way by considering the entire project. Once the
project name is decided, it's
time to find out who will use the Movie Booking System.
Of course, we need to ask the domain expert for this information.
And we know that there are customers and managers.
One element that is easy to miss in the early stages of design
is external dependencies.
External dependencies
could be existing legacy systems or
payment systems.
These dependencies can have a
significant impact on the overall system design, so it's
important to identify them as early as possible.
Fortunately,
elements such as payment gateways and legacy systems are
already used in existing systems, so they
can be identified relatively easily.
One of the elements that is easy to overlook in dependencies is
external environmental factors.
Korea is in the same time zone, but in a
large country, each theater has a different time zone.
So, the Movie Booking System is
inevitably affected by the environmental factor of time zone.
These factors are easy to miss unless you ask the domain expert directly.
Domain experts are good at identifying these aspects.
Since we might consider it trivial and skip the explanation, now that we have
specified the dependencies, let's
focus on the internals of the Movie Booking System.
First, let's ask a domain expert what the customer does in the Movie Booking System.
What does the customer do?
Customers perform tasks such as searching for movies,
viewing movie details,
selecting a showtime,
selecting a seat,
booking a movie,
checking reservation details, and
canceling a reservation.
Are choosing a showtime and selecting a seat part of the process of booking a movie?
And isn't reserving a movie ticket and canceling a reservation
ultimately the same as purchasing a ticket and getting a refund?  That's right.
Since this is a familiar domain, you could have asked if
selecting a showtime and selecting a seat were
part of the process of booking a movie ticket.
However, if it's an unfamiliar domain, you'll repeat several refinement processes while
analyzing each use case in detail.
Depending on the project situation,
this process may be repeated several times, but the more
leisurely and meticulously you analyze, the less trial and
error you'll experience during the design and implementation stages.
Based on our conversation so far, we've
organized the customer's use cases into four categories.
Next is the administrator. You
can see that the administrator has five management items.
Personally, I tend to be careful with the word "Manage" in development. It's
too general an expression, so it's
unclear what the job is. This is also the case
here. I'm not sure
how to specifically manage.
Through conversations with domain experts, we
expanded each management item into a specific use case.
In an actual project,
there would be more use cases than this, but I've
simplified it for the sake of explanation. What's
notable here is that creating a showtime also
creates a ticket.
And you
can also see that an external service called a payment gateway is used to purchase or refund tickets.
I've combined the customer and administrator use cases.
Looking at the entire set of use cases like this,
something feels missing.
There's adding a theater, but there's nothing
like searching for a theater.
It seems like there are quite a few use cases that are not visible.
From a domain expert's perspective, there is a lot to explain, so
use cases that seem obvious can be
omitted.
So, what about from a developer's perspective?
Wouldn't it be more helpful for document management to omit simple news cases like searching for theaters?
If it's a backend design, it seems okay to omit
simple use cases like searching for a theater. It's
not too late to respond during the implementation phase.
However, for an actual project,
these use cases are a good starting point for the screen planner. The
planner can look at the use case for searching for a theater and think about
how to enable searching for a theater. When you
merge the diagrams, it looks complicated. In an
actual project, it would be much more complicated. In
this case, there is no need to forcefully merge them. I
merged them here just to reveal that there are missing cases. I
filled in all the missing cases.
There is a use case where the connection to the actor is omitted.
This means that it applies to both the customer and the manager.
And I wrote it in English for the convenience of implementation. It's
okay because it's a small project now, but
if the project is large and complex, the
domain expert may be at a loss as to where to start explaining.
What does a manager do?  It's
a lot of work, as expected from an
administrator. In
this case, it's a
good idea to consider whether the actors can be subdivided. Although it
was initially called an administrator, it may be possible to
subdivide by role.
And there may be an external service that uses the Movie Booking System. If the
actors are subdivided like this, the
domain expert will be able to provide information in a more systematic way.
Of course, this is just one example of analyzing a complex domain. There may be many
other good methods. It is
important to respond flexibly according to the situation.
Conclusion: In
this session, we used a use case diagram to
set the project's goals and
proceeded with the initial stages of analysis.
Personally, I think analysis is the most difficult part of the entire development process. This is
because the most abstract and vague concepts need to be organized.
Next time, we will analyze the main use cases in
more detail. Thank you for your hard work
so far.